and now it's my turn to review the
factory pattern let's go to code
[Music]
as I mentioned in the sources for
this course we're going to see the
factory pattern of the factory pattern well we can
analyze the diagram that is being
indicated here look we have a
figure interface and we have three
implementations of this interface
circle square and rectangle then we
have a class that is the factory and
well this comes to be the test class
to execute our application itself the
important thing would be all this
together with this factory class let's
understand that the factory design pattern
its objective is to return
instances of a particular class
by means of some identifier
so for example if I need to
have an instance of the person class
I am going to tell the factory I need
an object of the person class if I
need for example of the ticket class
I have to go first through the factory and
the factory will be responsible for
returning that instance to me that is to say I am not
going to directly distance the object
and for that a peculiar demonstrative example is not brought
so that you can
understand this let's look we have
an app class here that comes to be the
execution of my method you can
see that I say now which  mysql h2 but I
'm entering a concept called
factory and I get a connection based on
some identifier and this returns
an instance and I can now use
the methods of that instance
so that this is understood first we are going
to explain the safe interface that in this
case would be replaced by the interface and
connection ok and connection for me
would be the interface in which I am going to
define two methods to connect and
disconnect to the database and then I
have my own implementations of this
interface such as for example mysql connection
oracle connection post greg connection
sql connection and an empty connection
ok then in the mysql connection
I am going to define some criteria to
link the database
and here I can indicate the default values
and simply as I am
implementing this connection interface I
overwrite the connect and
disconnect methods at my discretion ok
you can put there the code that best
suits you that you need most for
connection now with very similar if I
am simply changing the
configuration parameters this can be
linked with some properties file it
depends on you but what I want to
exemplify here is the use of the
pattern look we have the dessert connection the
same other values sqlserver  and an
empty connection where we indicate that
no provider was specified well
then according to the diagram we would already have
this part and its implementations
now we need the factory the
factory or the factory would be this
connection factory class in which what I am
doing is having a public method that
returns a connection interface and here
because we put connection interface the
objective of this pattern is to return an
instance as requested by the user
so how we are making a
database connection factory
is that context to
return some implementation that
obviously depends on this interface and
connection if I put sqlserver connection
here it would be returning an
implementation only of sql if I
establish dessert it would only be
returning dessert so in order to
have that independence from
any engine that I can return
according to some identifier it is necessary to
place an interface with that I make
the code flexible and well I am going to
call a connection method that would be
similar here get safe which would be to
obtain figure simply first
receive a parameter that I am going to indicate
some database engine and evaluated if
the engine comes did not read it I am going to
return an empty connection if the engine
is equal to mysql then I am going to
return an instance of  mysql
connection mysql which is this
class
and therefore to distance the constructor is not executed
and I already have the values
initializes 2 so that I can
later make a connect or disconnect
according to the convenience that I need the same
way for oracle I return an instance of
now which for dessert the same seems to be
worth the same and so for each
database engine that I may need if
any does not meet the criteria I can
return an empty connection the class that
executes all this would be app where in
the main method an instance of a factory
created the factory and then used the same
factory to indicate a connection and
passed it the identifier that I need if I
want to connect on this occasion now
with would be the one that now with I can now have
its connect and disconnect if I
want from mysql the same and if I want from
h2 the same then in that way when
executing the application we will see that we have
different instances according to
the identifier that we
need
then you can see at the bottom
that it says it connected now with it it
disconnected from now which
mysql connected and the same for the following
cases
in this case as h2 is not within the
factory set it says that it is not
specified  the provider now this is a
demonstrative exercise in which
you can also apply to another
context if you have any
need to define objects according to
some characteristics you can have that
class already implemented and simply by
calling it through the factory you
can have the instance and what is the
benefit of this the benefit is
mainly the flexibility that
the code gives us by not depending on
any particular instance because
because we will simply have to
go through the factory first and the factory would
give us the implementation that we
need and so we could change one
piece for another depending on the context of the
application in the next tutorial
we will see the abstract factory pattern or abstract factory
or abstract factory
as you want to call it in which we are going to
have a factory of factory and we will be
able to obtain objects according to the
factory that we are looking for if you liked
this tutorial
give it a thumbs up share it with your
friends don't forget to subscribe in the
button below follow me on
social networks that are in the description of the
video leave your comment and I'll wait for you in
a next tutorial
[Music]